{\fs31\fsp3\fad(300,660)\c&HD6E2D8&\4c&H000000&\fscy100\1a&H0A&\b0\pos(239.971,327.971)}比尔·康顿 执导
{\fs32\fsp3\fad(300,400)\c&HD6E2D8&\4c&H000000&\fscy100\1a&H0A&\b0\pos(222.496,330.432)} 伊恩·麦凯伦
{\fs32\fsp3\fad(300,400)\c&HD6E2D8&\4c&H000000&\fscy100\1a&H0A&\b0\pos(207.686,328.4)}劳拉·琳妮
福尔摩斯先生
你不该那麽做
You shouldn't do that.
敲打玻璃
Tap the glass.
你怎麽知道我这麽打算的
How did you know I was going to?
还请见谅  我儿子很爱蜜蜂
You must forgive my son. He loves bees.
这不是蜜蜂  这是黄蜂
It isn't a bee. It's a wasp.
完全不是一回事
Different thing entirely.
那是他吗
Was that him?
啊  浪子归巢
Ah, the prodigal returns.
出去  罗杰  你知道不能进这里的
Outside, Roger. You know you're not allowed.
跟养了一匹威尔士小马驹一样
Like having a Welsh pony.
你要上楼去书房吗
Will you be going up to your study?
不  先不上去
No, not as yet.
啊  舒服  又回家了
Ah, yes. Home again.
终于回家了
Home again.
门罗太太
Mrs. Munro!
我们遭遇了人口减少事件
It would appear we've had a decrease in population.
我不在的时候希利先生有来照料蜂房吗
Did Mr. Healy not come by to take care of the apiary whilst I was gone?
来了  不过他下次就不能帮忙了
Yes, but he won't be able to do it next time.
- 他说的吗  - 不是  他女儿说的
- Did Mr. Healy say that?  - No, his daughter did.
她带他搬走一起住了  她说他太虚弱了
She's taken him to live with her. Too feeble, she said.
-  他很虚弱吗  - 看著精神头倒是挺好的
- Is he too feeble?  - Seemed spry enough.
- 比以前爱聊天了  也许  - 和你吗
- Chattier, maybe.  - With you?
自言自语
With himself.
书房钥匙
Key to the study.
- 那是午饭吗  - 嗯
- Is that lunch?  - Mm.
华生已经结婚了  我还是孤身一人
Watson had married and I was alone.
事实上  就是在那天  他离开了贝克街
In fact, it was on the very day he left Baker Street
也是在那天  我的最后一案拉开序幕
that the case which was to be my last began to unfold.
大约30年前  一战结束
It was almost 30 years ago. The Great War had ended
游客们也来到贝克街观光
and the tourists had come back to Baker Street
想看一眼真实的夏洛克·福尔摩斯
to catch a glimpse of the real Sherlock Holmes.
还好在华生在故事里
Thankfully, in his stories,
用假地址
Watson had always published a false address
代替了我们真实的住所
for our actual quarters.
看来你找到了正确的地址
So you found the right address.
- 你为什麽要这麽做呢  - 先生
- Why did you do it?  - Sir?
闯进我的书房
Break into my study.
我的书房是至圣之所
My study is my sanctum sanctorum.
私人领地
Private place.
你去日本之前  我看到你在写那个故事
Before you went to Japan, I saw you writing that story.
我不知道你竟然写故事
I didn't know you wrote stories.
噢  华生医生  他是作者
Oh, Dr. Watson, yes, he was the writer.
所以  我跟妈妈借了钥匙进了你的书房
Well, so I borrowed Mum's key and went into your study,
它就在那里
and there it was.
你看了多少了
And how much did you read?
就到你停下来的那里  那部分很好看
Just to where you stopped. It was a good part too.
一个男人来到贝克街
A man comes to Baker Street.
你说  你是为你妻子而来的
You say, "You've come about your wife."
你怎麽看出来的  你有没有做那件事
How could you tell? Did you do the thing?
做什麽事
What thing would that be?
手杖上有狗的牙印
"The cane shows the marks of a dog's teeth.
木材来自马德拉西南部的一个岛上
The wood is from an island southwest of Madeira."
这种事情
That thing.
你怎麽知道那个男人是为他妻子来的
And how would you tell that a man's visit was about his wife?
他戴了婚戒吗
He wears a wedding ring?
没  线索都在那一页上
No. The clues are all on that page.
确切来说  在这句话里
This sentence, to be exact.
一天  房间里进来一个年轻人
"One day, into the room came a young man,
穿著一身刚刚熨烫过  却不甚昂贵的衣服
in newly-pressed, albeit inexpensive clothes."
衣服刚熨烫过  但他是个年轻的男性
The clothes are freshly-pressed. He's a young man, though.
衣服不贵
Not expensive clothes.
所以一定是他妻子给他熨衣服  男人没这个才能
Then his wife must press them. Men don't have the talent
他也请不起僕人
and he can't afford a servant to do so.
很不错
Very good.
- 你是这麽知道他是为妻子而来的  - 嗯  并不是
- That's how you knew it was about the wife.  - Well, no.
如果你是个侦探  而一个男人来找你
When you're a detective and a man comes to visit you...
通常都是为了他的妻子
it's usually about his wife.
所以你为什麽到这就停了
So why did you stop where you did?
你从药店那把东西拿来了吗
Ah, did you get the things from the chemist?
下订单了  说需要等几天
On order. Said it would be a few days.
我们得盯著他们弄好
We'll hold them to that.
除此之外一切都非常成功是吗
Otherwise, triumphant, were you?
成功得和二战胜利日一样
Like V-E Day.
噢  医生来了
Oh. Doctor's here.
- 你在日本感冒了吗  - 像是这样吗
- Did you catch cold in Japan? - Does it sound it?
我以为你终于了结了什麽事
I thought you might be coming off the tail end of something.
- 体重也轻了  - 嗯
Lost some weight as well. - Hmm.
你找到你要的了吗
Did you find what you were looking for,
神秘的椒山岩
the mysterious ashy prick?
岩山椒
Prickly ash.
噢  不好意思 那家伙就是为了这个邀你去日本的  对吗
Oh, yes, sorry. That was the reason the fellow invited you to Japan, wasn't it?
挖出一堆东西  走私回家
Dig up a pile of the stuff, smuggle it home?
它不会影响到你开的药物的作用
It can't interfere with anything you've prescribed.
- 但是它也不可能让我生病吧  - 单凭它  不会
- But surely it can't do me ill.  - In and of itself, no.
- 你是说有副作用  - 有可能
- You mean there might be side effects?  - Perhaps.
- 比如呢  - 希望
- Such as?  - Hope.
请你去日本的那个人叫什麽
What was the name of the fellow who invited you to Japan?
你刚和那个人一起呆了一个星期
You just spent a week with the man,
书信来往有几个月了
corresponded with him for months.
你还记得他的名字吗
Do you recall his name?
我诊所附近的一间公寓马上要出租了
There's a flat adjacent to my surgery that's gone to let...
不要
No!
要是你不记得电话在哪怎麽办
What happens when you don't recall where the telephone is,
或者你忘了把煤气关上
or you forget to turn off the gas?
- 你不能一个人住著  - 我不是一个人住
- You can't live alone.  - I don't live alone.
我有管家
I have the housekeeper.
拿著这本日记
Take this diary.
每次你不记得一个名字或者地方
Each day you don't recall a name or place,
就在日记本上的那天做个记号
make a mark on the page for that day's date.
要是我忘记做记号呢
And if I forget to make the mark?
不 不 不 不要
No, no, no. No. No, no, no.
- 这是蜂王浆  - 以后我们不用这个了
- It's the royal jelly.  - Yes, well, we're not using it anymore.
我们用这个
Instead, we're going to use this.
- 它叫岩山椒  - 这是吃的吗
- It's called prickly ash.  - Is it food?
唉  看著像是下水道里挖出来的
Eurgh. Looks like it came out the down-spout.
从日本来的
It came from Japan.
难怪这麽可怕
That makes all the difference.
像用蜂王浆一样把它加到茶和咖啡里
You add it in as you would the royal jelly, in the tea or the coffee.
而且你应该试试用这个做饭
And you should try cooking with it
让你的拿手菜更上一层楼
to enhance your specialities.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes?
民喜梅崎
Tamiki Umezaki.
欢迎来日本
Welcome to Japan.
您能接受邀请  我真是深感荣幸
I am so honoured you have accepted my invitation.
今晚在我家过夜  明天我们开始搜寻
We spend tonight at my house. Tomorrow we begin our search.
您的这本书我收藏二十年了
I have owned your book for 20 years.
第一次印刷出版的时候我就买了
I purchased my copy when it first appeared in print.
我希望您赐我一个签名
I hope you'll do me the honour of a personal inscription.
噢  好  当然了
Oh, yes. Of course.
梅崎先生  岩山椒生长的地方离这儿多远
Mr. Umezaki, how close to the city does the prickly ash grow?
大部分生长在海边
It is found mostly near the sea.
我们得走多远
And how far shall we have to go?
坐火车需要两天
Where I am thinking is two days' journey by train.
您很心急吗
You are very eager?
有个项目我正进行到一半  我想早点完成
I'm in the middle of a project that I'm keen to finish
我的思维得保持在最佳状态
and my wits must be at their sharpest.
我希望能尽快从它的药效中获益
I want to be able to benefit from the effect as soon as possible.
- 有那麽急吗  - 恐怕是的
- It's that urgent?  - I fear it's so.
您是个很伟大的侦探
You are very great detective!
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
我妈妈想知道你您有没有带那顶大名鼎鼎的帽子
My mother, she wonders if you have brought your famous hat.
噢  那顶猎鹿帽
Oh, the deer stalker.
那是插画师臆想出来的
That was an embellishment of the illustrator.
我从没戴过
I've never worn one.
- 那烟斗呢  - 我更喜欢雪茄
- And the pipe?  - I prefer a cigar.
我和华生说过  如果我哪天要亲自写点什麽
I told Watson, if I ever write a story myself,
那一定是为了纠正因为他的想像而造成的
it will be to correct the million misconceptions
那些成百上千的错误认识
created by his imaginative licence.
您写了吗
Did you write such a story?
我现在打算写了
But I'm trying to do so now.
我必须在死之前瞭解此事
I must finish with you before I die.
所以你是为你妻子来的
"So you've come about your wife."
你是为你妻子来的
"You've come about your wife."
你是
"You've come..."
罗杰
Roger.
这儿
Here.
午饭后见
I'll see you after lunch.
我需要你帮忙料理蜜蜂
I'm going to need some help with the bees.
所以你找到正确的地址了
So you found the right address.
221B好心的门卫告诉了我地址
A friendly porter at 221B.
只是为了误导好奇的人们  小小地虚构了一下
It's just a minor fiction to mislead the curious.
大部分都是美国人
Most of them seem to be American.
请坐  凯尔默先生
Have a seat, Mr. Kelmot.
那麽
So...
你是为你妻子来的
you've come about your wife.
- 你怎麽知道的  - 不重要
- How did you know? - It doesn't matter.
把你要说的都告诉我吧
Tell me what you have to say.
我的妻子名叫安
My wife is named Ann.
她母亲在生产时去世了
Her mother died in childbirth.
她爸爸是个上校
Her father was a colonel,
在瓦济里斯坦的一次行动里丧生
killed in that business at Waziristan.
我们非常想要孩子
We wanted very much to have children.
怀第一个孩子的时候  她3个月就流产了
She lost our first child in her third month...
第二个孩子4个月流产
Our second in her fourth.
他们说  再怀孕会很危险
We were told it was too dangerous to try again.
安为此心烦意乱
Ann was... distraught.
就好像每次失去的都是一个真正的孩子  而不是
It was as though each of them lost had been a real child, as opposed to...
谢谢
Thank you.
有一次  她甚至坚持让我准备了一对刻好的墓碑
For a time, she even insisted I have a pair of headstones carved
放倒我们的墓地里去
and placed in our cemetery plot,
就好像他们的身体真的埋在下面一样
as if their bodies were buried beneath.
她极其需要做点什麽来缓解这种危险的忧鬱
She was in desperate need of something to soothe this dangerous melancholy.
她喜欢音乐  于是我建议她学学玻璃琴
She liked music so I suggested the glass armonica.
玻璃琴
The armonica?
我父亲最珍爱的物件
My father's most prized possession.
他每天都弹  直到他去世的那天为止
He played it constantly till the day he died.
我把琴带回家
I had it brought to the house
安排了一个月的课程
and arranged a month's worth of lessons.
每周一个小时
One hour per week.
很快  安就问我能不能增加课时  每周两次
Soon Ann asked me if she could increase the lessons to twice a week.
后来变成三次  再后来变成每天
Then three times. Then every day.
她培养起了这项新爱好  你也希望她这麽做
So, she took up the avocation you hoped she would.
你为什麽来找我  凯尔默先生
Why are you here, Mr. Kelmot?
福尔摩斯先生  我的安变了
Mr. Holmes, my Ann has changed.
而且不光是那些课 也不光是她对乐器的痴迷
And it isn't just the lessons or her obsession with the instrument.
有一次我在房间外面
One day I was outside the room
突然弹奏的声音停了
and suddenly her playing stopped.
接著我听到她说  声音很清晰
And I heard her saying, quite clearly...
格蕾丝  詹姆斯
Grace? James?
这是你们给孩子准备的名字
Those were to be the names of your children?
我当面问安的时候  她否认了
When I confronted Ann, she denied it.
所以我不再让她弹玻璃琴  也不再允许她上课
So I forbad her playing the armonica and I forbad her taking the lessons.
给她上课的那个女人  西莫尔女士
The woman who teaches them, Madame Schirmer,
是有危险信仰的人
is a person of dangerous beliefs.
一个音乐老师的危险信仰
The dangerous beliefs of a music teacher?
她给安施咒了
She's put a spell on Ann,
玩弄她本就脆弱的思想 我不知道原因
preying upon her weak frame of mind, for what reason I cannot say.
你有证据吗
Have you proof of this?
遵从我的要求 她不再见西莫尔女士了
Following my instructions, she stopped seeing Madame Schirmer.
但我在信箱里收到了3张这个女人发来的收据
I received in the post...three receipts from the woman.
每张对应一节玻璃琴课
Each for the payment of one armonica lesson.
又一次  安否认了这件事
Again Ann denied it.
因此  我禁止她再从银行里取钱了
Consequently, my wife is no longer permitted to withdraw money from the bank.
昨天  我跟踪了安
Then yesterday, I followed Ann
去了那个女人给她上课的地方
to the place where the woman gives her lessons.
我在人行道上都能听到她弹奏的声音
Even on the pavement below I could hear her playing.
于是我走进去  但那个西莫尔说她不在
Naturally, I went inside, but the Schirmer woman said,
你妻子不在这
"Your wife is not here."
昨晚  我质问安
Last night, I questioned Ann.
她说她没去过西莫尔女士的家
And she said that she hadn't been to Madame Schirmer's rooms.
近几周都没去过了
Not for weeks.
你有你妻子的肖像吗
Do you have a portrait of your wife?
回答最后一个问题  我就接你的案子
I shall take your case if you answer just one last question.
好的
Certainly.
你妻子用什麽香水
What perfume does your wife wear?
罗杰
Roger.
很晚了  外面亮得像那场大空袭一样
It's late. Lights out like it's the Blitz.
看看你
Look at you.
你还记得你爸爸吗
Do you remember your dad?
我记得他拉著我的手  带我去海边
I remember him holding my hand and taking me to the sea.
你不记得  那是照片里的
You're not remembering. That's the picture.
那些睡前现编的故事呢
What about the invisible stories?
有时候在睡前  你爸爸会编一些故事 他会
Some nights at bedtime, your dad would make up stories. He'd...
他会说  说三个东西
he'd say, "Give me three things."
你会说  球 猫和罗杰
And you'd say, "A ball, a cat and Roger."
然后他会
So then he'd...
他会编一些故事
he'd make up some tale
一个球有一隻猫  猫的名字叫罗杰
about a ball that had a pet cat named Roger.
从来都是一个这个  一个那个  和罗杰
Always a something and something and Roger.
你一个故事都不记得了
You don't remember any of the invisible stories?
不记得了  你记得吗
No. Do you?
我一直都不擅长讲故事
I was never any good at stories.
睡个好觉
Sleep well.
首先你得知道  这并不危险
The first thing to know is there's no danger.
蜜蜂没兴趣伤害你
Bees aren't interested in harming you.
它们唯一关心的就是自我保护
Their only concern is self-preservation.
- 避开人类吗  - 它们太聪明了 人类伤不了他们
- From people?  - They're much too clever for people.
他们的敌人是黄蜂  疾病和捕食者
Their enemies are the weather, disease and predators.
黄蜂是他们的头号天敌
The wasp is their particular antagonist.
你知道吗  一隻黄蜂可以在一分钟内杀死40只蜜蜂
Did you know that one wasp can kill 40 honey bees in under a minute?
因此  我们一点都不喜欢黄蜂
In consequence, we do not like wasps.
是  先生  我们不喜欢黄蜂
Yes, sir. We do not like wasps.
蜂后掌管整个群体
The queen runs the colony.
工蜂伺候蜂后
The drones service the queen.
手抬起来
Hands up.
工人就是要干活  理所应当
Workers do the work. As it should be.
我们需要关注的是最近蜂群数量的减少
Of concern is the latest decrease in the bee population.
找到了问题所在  现在我们得解决它
We've identified the problem, and now we must solve it.
好  找到了  走吧
Right. There you are. Off you go.
你被蜜蜂咬过吗
Have you ever been bitten by a bee?
是蛰  蜜蜂没有牙齿
Stung. Bees don't have teeth.
我被蛰过
Yes, I have.
不是经常发生吧
Well, not often, though.
7,816次
7,816 times.
我会计数的
I keep a record.
你看上去一点儿也不害怕
You're not entirely dreadful.
你被咬过吗
You ever been bit?
没  我还没被咬过
No. I have never been bit.
人们总是在和蜜蜂打交道  不是吗
Well, people work with bees all the time, don't they?
蜂王浆是什麽
What is royal jelly?
是工蜂的一种特殊分泌物
It's a special secretion of the worker bees.
- 名字里有个王是因为  - 这是给蜂后吃的
- And it's royal because?  - It feeds the queen.
对啦
Bravo.
蜂王浆的治癒能力促成了我的专著
It was the jelly's curative powers that prompted my monograph,
《蜂王浆的价值》一书
The Value of Royal Jelly
还有《有关岩山椒的潜在保健功能》
with Further Comments on the Potential Health Benefits of Prickly Ash.
- 那是什麽  - 岩山椒吗
- What's that?  - Prickly ash, hmm?
在日语里  这是是山椒的通称
Well, in Japanese,  hire sansho is the common word for zanthoxylum piperitum.
以前被拿来治疗各种退化性疾病
It's used to treat various degenerative diseases.
贫血  血液循环病  关节炎
Anaemia, circulatory conditions... arthritis and...
那个叫什麽
Hmm. What's it called?
噢  还有衰老
Oh. Senility.
那是在开玩笑
That was a witticism.
最近的研究表明岩山椒比蜂王浆还有营养
The newest research suggests that prickly ash has far more promise than royal jelly.
以后我们就认准它了
Henceforth, prickly ash is all that we should use.
你还写了关于这对夫妇的什麽了
Have you written more about the man and his wife?
- 别心急  - 是真的吗
- All in good time. - Is it real?
当然了 捏造的故事不值一钱
Of course. Fiction is worthless!
你停下的地方
The place you stopped.
为什麽你想知道他妻子的香水是什麽
Why do you want to know the wife's perfume?
- 玫瑰庄园是吗  - 对的
- Cameo Rose, is it?  - Yes.
总是会留香
Always leaves a trace.
西莫尔女士
Madame Schirmer.
西莫尔女士 我是托马斯·凯尔默 让我进去
Madame Schirmer, this is Thomas Kelmot. Let me in.
西莫尔女士
Madame Schirmer!
凯尔默 我警告过你
Herr  Kelmot, I did warn!
你再来我就要报警了
You come, I call the Metropolitan Police!
女士 我朋友是那种 如果你拒绝让我们进去
Madame, my friend's emotional state is such that, if denied entry,
他就可能会发脾气的人
he might not be able to restrain his passions.
让我们俩进去吧 我来负全责
Allow us both in, and I will take full responsibility.
- 感激不尽  - 这是哪位
- Thank you so much.  - Who is this?
- 这位先生是个侦探  - 是吗 请让我看看他的证件
- This gentleman is a detective. -  Ja?  His badge, please?
他的名字是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
His name is Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
你介意我关门吗 风好大
You don't mind if I close this, do you? Such a draught.
不介意 我在杂志上看过夏洛克·福尔摩斯
No. I have seen Sherlock Holmes in the magazines.
他是戴著帽子叼著烟斗的 绝对不是这个人
With the hat and the pipe. It was never this person.
西莫尔女士 我看到安进来
Madame Schirmer, I saw Ann enter this place,
我命令你交出她
I demand you produce her.
你妻子不在这里
Your wife is not here.
- 你上次就这麽说过  - 你是在质疑我的诚实度吗
- You said that last time. - You question my truth?
奥斯瓦尔德 亲爱的 我们想知道你是不是这位男士的妻子
Oswald, my dear, it is a wish to know if you are this man's wife.
- 不是  - 你可能在伪装
- No. - You could be in disguise.
- 我不这麽认为  - 看吧
- I don't think so. -  Voila!
那是英国人叫做厕所的地方
It is, I believe, what the English call a water closet.
她就在这 我看到过她
She was here! I saw her!
凯尔默先生 如果你坚持要找你妻子
Mr. Kelmot, if you insist on following your wife
而你又雇我去做同样的事情的时候
when you have employed me to do the same,
我们中的一个就会被解雇
one or the other of us will find himself made redundant.
- 他疯掉了  -他是个蠢货
- He is distraught.  - He is a fool.
玻璃琴过去被认为是用于黑魔法的
The armonica used to be thought of as an instrument of the black arts,
说是用于召唤死去的人的
said to be used to call for the dead.
这似乎和玻璃的特质有关
Something to do with the nature of the glasses.
你不会真觉得这是真的吧
You don't believe that, surely?
我信不信并不重要
What I believe plays no part in this matter.
凯尔默女士最后一次什麽时候来的
When was Mrs. Kelmot last here?
好几周之前
Weeks now.
所以你给她寄的是奥斯瓦尔德课程的收据
Then the receipts you posted to her address were for Oswald's lessons.
凯尔默在为他们买单
Mrs. Kelmot is paying for them.
弗拉·凯尔默很有热情 但依然不专业
Frau  Kelmot is passionate, but an amateur.
她知道奥斯瓦尔德有这个天赋
She knew it was Oswald who has the gift.
- 你知道她之前不在这里  - 当然
- You knew she was not here.  - Of course.
奥斯瓦尔德身上没有她的味道
Oswald doesn't wear her scent.
我还是不信你就是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
You are still not Sherlock Holmes!
真贴心
How considerate.
你在等我
You waited for me.
你在干嘛
What are you doing?
试试看能不能分辨出我去过哪里
Trying to see if I can tell where I've been.
你自己不知道吗
Don't you know?
福尔摩斯先生能通过观察一个人知晓很多事
Mr. Holmes can tell things like that just from looking at a person.
- 你上哪去  - 去看看蜜蜂
- Where are you off to?  - See to the bees!
你必须先把早餐吃掉
You'll eat your breakfast first!
我那天收到你阿姨的一封信
Got a letter from your aunt the other day.
她说在朴次茅斯有对夫妻开了一间旅馆
She says there's a couple in Portsmouth opening a hotel there.
正需要个管家
Need a housekeeper.
我们为什麽会想去住在朴次茅斯
Why would we want to live in Portsmouth?
- 我们不能永远呆在这里  - 为什麽不能
- Can't stay here forever.  - Why not?
- 我们就是不能  - 朴次茅斯有什麽
- Because we can't.   - What's in Portsmouth?
- 这对夫妻在那开了间旅馆  - 你说过了
- This couple are opening a hotel there...  - You said that.
你得把所有东西吃完了才能离开这张桌子
You'll leave the table when you're finished and not before.
我没吃完呢
I'm not finished.
你别吃那个日本垃圾
You don't eat that Japanese muck.
这可是岩山椒
It's  hiro sansho.
- 我知道你喜欢你喜欢在蜂房工作  - 那是个养蜂场
- I know you like working with the hive...  - It's an apiary.
并且你喜欢冒险 当然我们不该靠得太近
And you like being given responsibility, but I shouldn't get too close.
- 蜜蜂不咬人的  - 我不是在说蜜蜂
- Bees don't bite.  - I don't mean the bees.
福尔摩斯先生不可能永远呆在这里
Mr. Holmes won't be here forever.
你阿姨说旅馆说不定还能给你留个位置
Your aunt says this hotel might even take you on.
- 他们有行李搬运工和  - 他们已经有了
- They got porters and...  - Have porters.
好了
Finished.
药商把你的东西送来了
Chemist delivered your things.
要我叫罗杰来打开这个木箱吗
Shall I have Roger open the crate?
不用 我弄完自己来开
No. I'll see to it when I'm finished.
好的 先生
Yes, sir.
先生
Sir?
我知道罗杰是您的帮手  他是个好孩子
I know Roger's been a help to you. He's a good boy.
他总是那麽聪明伶俐
He's always been clever.
我和他父亲都不瞭解他感兴趣的事情
His dad and I weren't the sort to know the things a boy like Roger takes interest in.
杰出的孩子都有著平庸的父母
Exceptional children are often the product of unremarkable parents.
我有一个住在朴茨茅斯的姐姐
I've got a sister. She lives in Portsmouth.
她的几个熟人朋友在那里开了一家酒店
A couple of her acquaintants are opening a private hotel there,
他们想让我和罗杰过去
say they're willing to take Roger and me on.
你有一个姐姐
You have a sister?
真是没想到
Never would have thought it.
是薪水太少吗
Is this a matter of wages?
不
No.
我会考虑下这个提议
I shall take this under advisement.
你走的话  我妈妈会伤心的
My mother was sad to see you leave.
我现在为我没有戴猎鹿帽而感到抱歉
I'm rather sorry now I didn't bring the deerstalker.
你说过你从不戴那个
You said you never wore one.
是的  但这可能让她开心
Well, yes, but it would've pleased her.
她喜欢小说里的那个  而你是真实的
She wanted the fictional. You are the real.
我不这麽认为
Well, I'm not sure that's true.
我一直很真实  直到约翰将我变成小说人物
I think I was real once until John made me into fiction.
那之后我就没什麽选择了
And then after that, I had little choice.
要麽扮演成他描绘的角色
Play the part as he'd fashioned it,
要麽变得完全不同
or become its contradiction.
我其实很喜欢烟斗
I'm actually quite fond of a pipe,
但在烟斗成为我的标志后
but to smoke it, especially in public,
在公共场合抽看上去就很庸俗
after it became so well known a prop, seemed vulgar.
所以华生医生的想像影响了你
So, Dr. Watson's imagination changed you?
我不喜欢想像
I've never had much use for imagination.
我更喜欢事实
I prefer facts.
当我还是个孩子时  我父亲带我来这里
My father would bring me here as a child.
这里被设计成微缩景观
It was designed as a miniature.
我们在这里像巨人一般
We walk as giants.
这些石头代表他所失去的生命
The stones represent the lives of those he has lost.
夏洛克先生
Sherlock-san!
- Hire sansho  - 岩山椒
- Hire sansho?  - Prickly ash.
- 福尔摩斯先生  - 嗯
- Mr. Holmes. - Hmm?
现在检查蜜蜂太迟了吗
Too late to check on the bees?
一点儿也不
Not in the least.
蜜蜂检查
Bee check!
- 它们很淡定   - 是的
- They're quiet.  - Yes.
当蜜蜂死后会怎麽样
What happens when the bees die?
这算是一个玄学问题吗
Is this a metaphysical question?
我的意思是 你会悼念他们吗
I mean, do you mourn them?
我从未悼念过他们
Oh, I can't say that I've ever mourned
不管是蜜蜂的死亡还是其他的灭亡
the dead, bees or otherwise.
我更关注当下
I concentrate on circumstances.
他们怎麽死的 谁要为此负责
How did it die? Who was responsible?
死亡 悲伤 悼念 这都很常见
Death, grieving, mourning, they're all commonplace.
而逻辑十分稀有
Logic is rare, and so...
我专注于逻辑
I dwell on logic.
谢谢 好心的先生
Well, thank you, kind sir.
- 晚安 蜜蜂  - 好梦  蜜蜂
- Night, bees.  - Sweet dreams, bees.
我们明天去游泳怎麽样
Now, what do you say we go for a dip tomorrow?
- 在海里  - 是的
- In the sea? - Yes.
- 水可能会凉的  - 对血液循环好
- It'll be brisk.  - Good for the blood!
好吧
All right, then.
你喜欢什麽类型的书
What sort of books do you like, hmm?
除了华生的故事和与蜜蜂相关的
Apart from Dr. Watson's stories and books about bees.
我只有这两种书
Those are all the books I have.
这里就有一个很好的图书馆
Well, there's a perfectly good library right here, inside.
你可以拿走任何你喜欢的书
You can take any book you like.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes?
我们要去游泳了吗
Are we going for our swim?
我已经检查过蜜蜂了
I've already seen to the apiary.
你还好吗
Are you all right?
我很好 我很
I'm perfectly... I'm quite...
特别好
Perfectly fine.
好吧 罗杰
All right, Roger.
你先走  我一会儿赶上你
You go along. I'll catch you up.
罗杰 快来  要不今天要浪费了
Roger! Come along or we'll lose the day.
很好
Well done.
这是她的照片吧
The photograph is her, isn't it?
故事里的那个女人
The woman in the story.
是的
Yes.
她是你写书的原因吗
Is she why you're writing it?
我并不是在写
I wouldn't say I was writing it...
我在试著记起它们
It's more I'm trying to remember it.
谢谢
Ah, thank you.
几个月前 我的哥哥麦考夫去世了
A few months ago, my brother Mycroft died.
他的第欧根尼俱乐部
His club, the Diogenes,
让我去伦敦取回他的东西
asked that I go up to London to retrieve his things.
他们给我一个小箱子 里面有华生写的故事
I was given a small chest  containing the Watson stories,
我一则都没有读过
none of which I'd ever actually read.
就像约翰通常说的那样
They were as John  always described them,
它们是用散文形式写出来的惊悚小说
penny dreadfuls with an elevated prose style.
但是其中过一个标题 激发了我的兴趣
But one of the titles  piqued my interest.
故事很熟悉
The story was familiar,
但结局很不对劲
but its ending felt very,very wrong.
我从没看过任何电影改编
I'd not seen any of the cinematic depictions.
但幸运的是  很快就有了这样一个机会
But by a fortunate chance, an opportunity soon arose.
看到一个人在银幕上有十二米高
It's strange to see a semblance  of one's self 40 feet high...
- 我为安的清醒感到担忧  - 因为她的神智清晰而担忧
-  I fear for my Ann's sanity.   -  Fear for her sanity?
年轻人  你应该担心自己的生命
Dear man, you should fear for your life.
什麽意思
Whatever do you mean?
谋杀 凯尔莫先生  这是谋杀
Murder, Mr. Kelmot. Murder.
然后像演哑剧一样被演出来的感觉很奇怪
...and played as a character out of pantomime.
下毒
Poisoned?
到底什麽意思
With what means have I?
你的玻璃琴 西莫尔女士
Your armonica,  Madame Schirmer.
- 荒唐  - 或者说是玻璃
-  Preposterous!   -  Or rather, the glasses.
是玻璃里的导线让它有了独特的声音
It is the lead in the crystal that creates the unique tone.
毒药通过皮肤被血液吸收
Absorbed into the blood  through the skin,
很少的量就可以让人产生幻觉
small exposure can produce  confusion, hallucinations.
持续接触导致精神错乱与死亡
But constant, obsessive contact  can end in insanity and death.
每个转折点都以捻鬍鬚来标志开始
Every plot twist  came with a twirl of a moustache
又以感叹号代表结束
and ended  in an exclamation mark.
这场未遂的谋杀设计得十分巧妙
Our would-be murderer is ingenious.
你不会是说
Surely you're not  referring to...
凯尔莫夫人  您需要为您自己
I'm afraid, Mrs. Kelmot,  you will have to find yourself
找一个新的音乐老师了
a new music teacher.
哦
Oh.
全是垃圾
Absolute rubbish!
那个德国女人有什麽动机杀安呢
What possible motive could that German woman have had to kill Ann?
那晚我一直在寻找
That night I searched for something
试图记起原本的案件
to jog my memory of the actual case.
找到了
And there it was...
她的照片
Her picture.
你知道 几年前 我能告诉你
You know, a few years ago, I could have told you everything
照片里的女人的任何事情
about the woman in that photograph.
当然 我能记起她最后是
Certainly I'd recall what had become of her,
受害者还是凶手
whether she was victim or culprit.
但是那晚
But that night...
我不记得任何事了
I couldn't remember any of it.
我唯一记得就是那是我的最后一案
All I knew for certain was that the case was my last
是我退出侦探生涯  到这里来
and it was why I left the profession, came down here,
养蜜蜂的原因
retired to my bees.
所以我决定把这个案子原原本本地写下来
So, I decided to write the story down on paper
而不是像约翰写的那种
as it was, not as John made it.
在我死前纠正它
Get it right before I die.
你不会死的
You're not going to die.
罗杰 我已经93岁了
Roger. I'm 93.
我有一个叔叔活到了102岁
I had a great uncle who lived to be 102.
噢  这可决定了我的命运
Well, then, that seals my fate.
你认识两个人都活这麽久的几率能有多少
What are the odds that you would know two men who would live that long?
好吧 那我不认识他
Well, I didn't actually know him.
我要去检查蜜蜂了
I'll see to the bees.
- 哦 福尔摩斯先生  - 福尔摩斯先生
- Ow! Mr. Holmes!  - Mr. Holmes!
啊  啊
Aargh. Aargh.
我被蛰了
I've been stung.
与黄蜂不同 蜜蜂会把刺留下
Unlike the wasp, the bee always leaves its sting.
我一定是做了什麽蠢事
I must have done something stupid.
不 没有 有时候就会无缘无故被蛰
Oh, no. Sometimes... there's no reason at all.
喝点儿盐水
Right. Salt water, you drink that.
或者用洋葱汁以防感染
Or onion juice to prevent serious consequences.
不要告诉你妈妈
And no need to tell your mother about all this.
我们可不想让她担心  对吧
We don't want to worry her, do we?
你会继续写那个故事的吧
You going to go back to the story?
这算是你的封口费吗
Is that the price for your silence?
我什麽都不说
Tight lips.
下午好
Good afternoon.
- 先生您需要什麽  - 要点茶  靠窗的位置
- Sir? - Tea for one in the window.
没问题先生  小心台阶
Certainly, sir. Mind the step.
你是说他病了吗
Ill, do you say?
只是写张支票就花费了他全部力气
Took all the strength he had just to write out the cheque.
- 您的茶 先生  -谢谢
- There you are, sir. - Thank you.
您的现金
Well, here we are.
- 你以前用过这个吗  -从没有
- Have you used this before? - No. I haven't.
这个毒性强劲  只要一滴就绰绰有馀
It is highly poisonous. A drop will more than suffice.
谢谢
Thank you.
只是托马斯现在
It's just Thomas is in such a state.
非要让我确定一下
He insisted I made certain.
请告诉科尔莫先生
Reassure Mr. Kelmot
自从他口授遗嘱以来没有改动过任何细节
that the particulars of the will have not changed since he dictated them.
你的财产会指定赠予给他  他的会给你
Your possessions are bequeathed to him, as his are to you.
- 抱歉  打扰一下  - 小姐  怎麽啦
- Excuse me. - Yes, miss?
8:10的那趟是快车吗
Is the 8:10 the fast service?
8:10那趟是慢车  中间经停的
The 8:10's the slow one, makes local stops.
那9:05那趟呢
And the 9:05?
那趟是快车  直达的
That's the fast train, goes right on through.
- 全部上车  -谢谢您
- All aboard! - Thank you.
全部上车
All aboard.
啊  蜜蜂都被你吸引了
Honeybees are attracted to you.
是香味  玫瑰庄园的味道
It's the scent. Cameo Rose.
- 哦  -她以为你是朵花呢
- Oh. - She thinks you're a flower.
这个小家伙现在肯定已经晕头转向了
Must confuse the little thing no end.
我能坐下吗
May I?
坐吧
Oh.
非常感谢
Very kind.
啊  鸢尾花  生长能力惊人的东西
Ah. The iris. Amazing resilience.
只要有足够的阳光  它们就能长得飞快
Enough light and they will grow
即使在最贫瘠的地方也是如此
in the most uninhabitable regions,
不管是沙漠  冻土  还是石缝里
desert, cold, rock.
你觉得为什麽
Why do you suppose it is
像鸢尾一样渺小不起眼的植物
that something as small and insignificant as the iris
比我们更强大呢
should be so much stronger than we are?
也许是因为他们更少受到外界的影响
Perhaps they're less affected by what goes on around them.
- 你是个植物学家吗  - 只是业馀爱好
- Are you a botanist?  - Amateur only.
我经常沉溺在某种爱好当中不能自拔
I am, by disposition, a hobbyist.
事实上  我有一个特殊的爱好
In fact, if I may, there is one particular hobby
大概能博您一笑
of mine that might amuse you.
我能预见未来
I can see the future.
我能看看你的掌纹吗
Shall I read your palm?
我发誓不会有什麽可怕的事情
I promise I'll find nothing dreadful.
那我们的蜜蜂朋友怎麽办
What about our friend?
- 哦  -哦
- Oh.  - Oh.
你的父母都已经不在了
Your parents are gone.
你母亲很早就去世了  你的父亲最近才离世
Your mother long ago, your father more recently.
你一直爱著一个
You had love in your heart for someone...
不  不止一个人
No, for more than one person.
但是他们都离开了你
But they have left you,
所以你的爱无处可去
and your love for them has nowhere to go.
你很痛苦
You're in pain.
但是你又不能让痛苦左右你的行为
But you must not allow your pain to guide your actions.
你会被引向哪儿呢  你的掌纹模糊不清
Where that leads... The lines are not so distinct.
- 为什麽  -什麽
- Why? - I beg your pardon?
你能看到这麽多
You see so much.
可你为什麽看不到接下来会发生什麽呢
Why can't you see what happens next?
-你的掌纹  -你说过了
- The lines... - Yes, you said.
把你那套夸夸其谈的小伎俩用到别处去吧  福尔摩斯先生
Ply your parlour tricks elsewhere, Mr. Holmes.
等等
Wait.
不行
I can't...
我什麽都不记得了
I can't remember.
妈妈  妈妈
Mum! Mum!
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
他是吸了那阵烟才昏过去的吗
Was it the smoke knocked him out?
有可能
Could have done.
更有可能是他站起来的时候太快了
Most likely he stood up too quickly
一下子失去了意识
and lost consciousness.
这已经不是第一次了
It isn't the first time.
上一个管家遇到这种情况直接手足无措
The last housekeeper didn't know what to do.
他肯定是打算给自己注射这个来著
He must have decided to take it subcutaneously.
好吧  现在我们走不了了
Well, now we can't leave.
他倒是保证了这一点
No. Made sure of that, didn't he?
岩山椒呢
Where's the hire sansho?
就是那些美洲花椒
The prickly ash.
如果它不在那儿  那我也不知道
If it's not there, I'm sure I don't know.
- 你是把它扔了吗  - 我干嘛扔它
- Did you throw it out?  - Why would I do that?
因为你对它怀有愤怒和厌恶
For spite and malice.
你从哪儿学到的这种词
Where'd you get words like that?
字典上
The dictionary.
十有八九他拿著那些垃圾
Like as not, he took the muck himself.
把它们和信一起全烧了
Got burnt up with the rest of it.
那玩意可助燃了
Those can go on the fire.
是福尔摩斯先生让你烧的吗
Did Mr. Holmes say you were to do this?
他经常那样烧信的
He always disposes of that sort.
你怎麽知道那些信里都有什麽
How do you know what sort these are?
你想知道都是谁在给他写信
You want to know who writes to him?
自以为破了开膛手杰克案的老年人
Pensioners who think they've solved Jack the Ripper.
丢了猫的寡妇
Widows who've lost their cats
觉得全世界只有福尔摩斯能帮她们把猫找回来
and just know he's the only man on Earth who can find them.
他是疯子们的最后一根救命稻草
He's the last resort for every lunatic out there.
- 这不是你能决定的  - 这就是
- It's not your decision. - It is...
如果我一直要充当拿厨子薪水的医护人员的话
If I'm to be a full-bore medical staff at cook's wages.
他是个病人  他需要的是护士  不是管家
He's an invalid. Needs a nurse, not a housekeeper.
他只不过是昏倒了
All he did was took a fall.
你爷爷精神矍铄  老当益壮了60年
Your granddad was hale and hearty
然后一下子摔倒了
60 summers then he took a fall.
之后只活了三个星期
It was three weeks to the day he died.
他应该在医院或者护理中心之类的地方
Should be in hospital. That or one of them places.
他会好起来的
He'll get better!
他好起来的时候我们就走
And the day he does is the day we go.
明白了吗
Is that clear?
- 哦  -你有一封日本寄来的信
- Oh.  - Got a letter from Japan.
梅崎先生寄来的
It's from Mr. Umezaki.
- 你读过吗  -没  本来想读的
- Have you read it?  - No. Wanted to.
欲望是罪  你可是个天主教徒
Sin of desire. You're a Catholic.
妈妈说大部分寄给你的信都被你扔了
Mum says you throw out most of the letters you get.
你觉得这是为什麽
And why do you think that is?
给你写信的那些人想让你帮忙
The people who write want you to solve things.
你一旦读了他们的信  你就会忍不住想帮他们的
If you read their letters, you'd want to help.
哦  不  你太过奖了
Oh, no. You give me too much credit.
原因很简单  要是我读了
It's just if I were to read them,
我就会觉得有必要回信
I'd feel obliged to respond.
说不定梅崎先生是想让你回日本呢
Perhaps Mr. Umezaki's asking you to go back to Japan.
哦  我不会再回日本的
Oh. I'll never go back to Japan.
- 为什麽  - 旅途漫漫而年力衰微
- Why not?  - Long journey, old man.
- 可你之前就去了  - 那是以前
- You made it before.  - That was before.
说不定你还能再弄到些岩山椒呢
Maybe you could get more prickly ash.
那对我恢复记忆一点用都没有
The prickly ash hasn't made a bit of difference to my memory,
不比蜂王浆管用到哪儿去
any more than the royal jelly did.
好吧
Yes.
唯一能够对我的记忆有点帮助的就是你了
The only inspiration for any sort of recollections has been you.
继续  打开它
Go on. You open it.
他肯定是要告诉我他母亲去世了
He's writing to say his mother is dead.
你怎麽知道
How could you tell?
梅崎先生曾发誓永远不再联繫我
Mr. Umezaki swore that he would never contact me again.
唯一能够让他改变主意的
The only thing that would make him change his mind
就是他母亲的遗言了
would be a deathbed instruction from his mother.
一个好孩子总是会听妈妈话的
A good son always does what his mother asks.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
你不该下床的
You're not to be out of bed!
门罗太太  我刚刚数了一下台阶
Mrs. Munro, I have counted the steps
从床到窗户  从窗户到
from the bed to the window, from the window to the...
不行 没有人看著  你什麽都不能干
You're not to do anything on your own.
就该把你捆在床上的
You're to ring.
你应该摇铃的
I thought it was an imposition.
你要是没办法自理就更过分了
It will be an imposition if you lose your bearings
然后你又会倒在地板上  还得我来收拾你
and end up on the floor for me to collect!
没想到这居然已经成了劳资纠纷
I hadn't realised that this had become an industrial dispute.
我一直在试著
I've been trying to calculate the likelihood
计算在一个不毛之地发现岩山椒的可能性
that we should find hire sansho in a place so utterly devoid of life.
这种植物十分顽强也说不定呢
Perhaps it is life reasserting itself.
您的岩山椒
Hire sansho.
味道怎麽样
How does it taste?
我们可不是为了味道去找它的
It isn't for the taste that we sought it.
啊  走之前
Ah, now, before we leave,
有件事一定不能忘
there's something that I mustn't forget.
按照你要求的  我已经签好了
I've signed it, as you requested.
我并不确定你能不能看懂我的草书
Not certain you can read my scrawl.
致梅崎先生  其实并没有拥有这本书很久
"To Mr. Umezaki, who has not owned this book for long."
这本书在你手上的历史并没有20年
You haven't had this book for 20 years.
你是从图书馆弄来的
It came from the library.
这还有胶水的痕迹
The glue mark shows where you removed
说明你把贴在这的封装卡给撕掉了
the card jacket.
你对蜜蜂  蜂王浆  还有美洲胡椒根本一窍不通
You know nothing about bees or royal jelly or prickly ash.
能让你来这儿就够了
Enough to bring you here.
过去几个月来咱们一直通信
During our correspondence over the last few months...
你不熟悉我的名字吗
was my name not familiar to you?
-并没有  -那我父亲的名字呢
- No. - My father's, then?
益男梅崎
Masuo Umezaki?
我不认识你父亲
I never knew your father.
他曾经是个外交官  在伦敦工作  很多年前了
He was a diplomat in London, years ago.
他喜欢跟英国文化有关的一切
He loved all things English.
他送我的第一个礼物是个板球拍
The first gift he gave to me was a cricket bat.
这是第二个
The second was this.
英文版的  他说这对我的学习有帮助
In English, so as to "assist my education."
我咨询了一位伟大的侦探  夏洛克·福尔摩斯
"After consulting with the very great detective Sherlock Holmes,
我发现最好的办法
"I realise it's in the best interests of us all
就是我无限期地留在英国
"that I remain in England indefinitely.
从这本书里
"You will see from this book
你会发现他非常聪明睿智
"that he is a very wise and intelligent man,
并且他说  这件事绝不能掉以轻心
and that his say in this matter should not be taken lightly."
从那以后我们再也没有收到他的消息
We never heard from him again.
- 对不起  -我母亲已经快要去世了
- I'm sorry. - My mother is dying.
她日渐衰老  身边却没有丈夫陪伴  都是因为你
She grew old without a husband. All because of you.
我理解
I understand.
你最后一次收到你父亲的来信的时候
The last time you heard from your father
就是你第一次听到我名字的时候
was the first time you heard about me.
益男从你的生活中消失
Masuo vanished from your life and
而我以书的方式出现
I arrived... in the form of a book.
一个取代了另一个  就是这样
One replaced the other, as it were.
我建议你和你妈妈面对这个事实
I suggest you and your mother take whatever time you have
花多长时间都不为过
to come to terms with the facts of the case.
一个男人抛弃了他的家庭  写了个故事给儿子
A man abandoned his family and wrote his son a story.
他绝不是第一个以牺牲为幌子 来掩饰自己怯懦的人
He wouldn't be the first to cloak his cowardice in a flag of sacrifice.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
但我和你父亲从未相识过
But I never knew your father.
我不该再继续用疑问打扰您了
I shall not bother you any longer with my questions.
但如果岩山椒成功了  您会告诉我的吧
But if the prickly ash succeeds, you will let me know?
救命啊
Help.
帮帮忙
谢谢
Thank you.
我看起来就像被巴斯克维尔猎犬攻击了一样
I look like I've been attacked by the Hound of the Baskervilles.
- 可不能让妈妈看见你穿那件上衣  - 不会的
- Can't let Mum see you wearing that top. - No.
- 那是证据  - 是啊
- It's evidence. - Yes.
什麽的证据  谋杀吗
What of? A murder?
噢  我有东西要给你
Oh... I've something for you.
不是这隻手
No.
日本蜜蜂
Apis cerana japonica.
- 日本有蜜蜂  - 是的  和我们的蜜蜂一样
- They have bees in Japan? - Yes. Just like our bees.
只不过是日本籍
Only they're Japanese.
这是给你的  是个礼物
No, it's for you. It's a gift.
噢  谢谢
Oh. Thank you.
Arigato  日语中是这样说谢谢的
Arigato,  as they say in Japan.
有心事吗
Something the matter?
今天你又损失了很多蜜蜂
You lost another dozen bees today.
- 很多  - 你觉得原因是什麽
- A dozen? - What do you think it is?
爆发式的死亡
An outbreak of mortality.
可能是患了我们不知道的疾病
Could be a disease we've not seen before,
或是发生了突变
or a sudden mutation.
你拿来些尸体  我们来检查一下
You bring up some corpses and we'll examine them.
- 好的  先生  - 还有我的放大镜
- Yes, sir! - And my glass.
在书房  应该在其中一个抽屉里
Study. Should be in one of the drawers.
罗杰
Roger?
- 福尔摩斯先生今天感觉好些了  -  是麽
- Mr. Holmes feels better today. - Is that so?
福尔摩斯先生感觉好多了 我们马上要开始调查了
Mr. Holmes feels so much better, we're about to start an investigation.
调查什麽
Of what?
让我们损失了大量蜜蜂居民
The crime wave that has done away
的犯罪事件
with a number of our apiary's most prominent residents.
好的  如果你需要嫌疑犯  你知道到哪里找我
Well. If you need suspects, you know where to find me.
妈妈  等一下
Mum, wait.
我想只要我们要求  福尔摩斯先生就会做他擅长的那件事
I bet if we asked, Mr. Holmes would... do his thing.
就是只凭观察就推断出别人是谁
The thing he does where he tells people
以及他们去过哪里
who they are and where they've been, just from looking.
告诉妈妈她去了哪里  让她见识一下
Do Mum for her.
我想你妈妈不需要我来告诉她去过哪里
I'm sure your mother doesn't need to be told where she's been.
别拿蠢事打扰福尔摩斯先生
Let's not bother Mr. Holmes with any foolishness.
这不愚蠢  过来
It's not foolishness. Here.
你过来站到福尔摩斯先生面前  就像这样
You come and stand in front of Mr. Holmes. Just like that.
他会跟你讲  你去过哪里
And he will tell you where you've been.
讲吧
Do it.
你希望她转个圈吗
You want her to turn in a circle?
不  不需要
No, that won't be necessary.
转个圈
Turn in a circle.
你今天大多数时间都在外面
You've been away most of the day.
你裙子上的煤灰说明你乘火车去了朴茨茅斯
The soot on your dress attests that you went by train to Portsmouth,
因为除了这一条线路  附近所有的能够实现这麽长距离
as all other nearby rail lines which might accommodate
往返的铁路线都在修理中  有的无法修复
a return trip of this length are under repair or beyond it.
在朴茨茅斯  你去见了开旅馆的一对夫妻
In Portsmouth, you met the couple who run the hotel.
你的头髮和指甲显示你想要留下一个好印象
Your hair and nails are evidence that you wished to make a favourable impression.
他们给你提供了工作  你答应了
They made you an offer, you accepted.
你婉拒了茶  并没有去看望
You declined tea, and did not see the sister
你不怎麽喜欢的姐姐
for whom you have no particular fondness,
以我身体抱恙为借口  匆匆赶回来
using my indisposition as an excuse to hurry back.
- 这不是借口  - 你答应了吗
- It wasn't an excuse. - You accepted?
下週一开始
Start a week Monday.
我们俩都去
Both of us?
- 我们都要去  - 她要让我做一个擦鞋童
- We're both going. - She wants me to be a bootblack!
- 罗杰  - 她想让我跟她做一样的事情
- Roger! - She wants me to do what she does!
我所做的并没有什麽好羞耻的
There is no shame in what I do!
你抱怨得够多了  总是念刀事情多麽难办
You complain enough about it! Always going on about how hard things are.
你希望能有更好的工作
And you wish you had it better!
她几乎不识字
She can barely read!
追上她
Go after her.
去为你说的故意中伤的话道歉
Apologise for saying things that were meant to hurt.
你刚刚很残忍
You were cruel!
如果你不道歉  你会后悔的
If you don't apologise, you will regret it.
- 人们总这样说  - 因为这是事实
- People always say that. - Because it's true.
去说  我很抱歉
Moi, je regrette tellement.
- 你后悔吗  - 非常
- You regret... - So much!
你爸爸不喜欢他谋生的工作
Your dad hated what he did for a living.
车行里的技工  就像他的爸爸一样
Mechanic in a garage, like his dad before him.
当他应徵入伍时  他告诉我
When he got called up, he said to me,
亲爱的  我不会在富家子弟吉普车的
"My love, I'll not spend this war
油底盘下度过这场战争
"underneath the oil pan of some toff's jeep.
我要为英国皇家空军效力
I'm gonna put in for the RAF."
他也是这麽做的
So he did.
接受训练
He trained.
得到高分  被分配去驾驶布伦海姆式轰炸机和马克四型坦克
Scored high marks, got assigned to a Bristol Blenheim, Mark IV.
第一次飞行时在空中爆炸了
Blown out of the sky. First time up.
他所有在车辆调配场里的同事都毫髮无伤地回来了
All his mates who worked the motor pool came home without a scratch.
我不该说刚刚那些话的
I shouldn't have said what I said.
这就是一个教训
Lesson there, then.
不要想什麽说什麽
Don't say everything you think.
看
Look.
- 你怎麽找到它的  -  在你的书桌里
- How did you find that? - In your desk.
- 不可能吧  - 角落那里找到的
- Couldn't have. - The one in the corner.
我打开它之前都不知道它是个书桌
Didn't know it was a desk until I opened it.
噢  那不是我的书桌  那是约翰的
Oh, that's not my desk, it's John's.
他离开贝克街去成婚了  把书桌留在了那里
He left it at Baker Street when he went off to get married.
是的  它有一个隔层
Yes, and there's a secret compartment
里面就装著你笔下的那隻手套
containing the very glove you've been writing about.
我知道你说过华生医生并不能总是说对
I know you say Dr. Watson didn't always get things right,
但在那个故事中
but in the story...
我不再研究那个故事了
I am not working on that story anymore.
我知道  但在华生的故事中  的确有玻璃琴
Yes, but in Watson's story, he does have the armonica in it.
和德国女士以及那个手套
And the German lady. And that glove.
所以也许他说对了的
So maybe he did get things right.
不  这不可能
No, that's not possible.
约翰那时已经不在贝克街了
John had gone from Baker Street by then.
那为什麽它会在那里
Well, then why was it in there?
我不知道  就算我曾经知道  我也不记得了
I don't know! And if I ever did know, I don't remember.
如果不记得了 那你为什麽说它并不像
If you can't remember, then why couldn't the case have been a success
- 华生医生写的那样成功  - 因为这是我最后的案子
like Dr. Watson wrote it? - Because it was my last case.
如果我最后成功地了结了它
And if I'd brought it to a successful conclusion,
我就不能逃离我的职业
I wouldn't have left the profession
在与世隔绝的这里度过35年
and spent 35 years here, in this place, away from the world!
我选择被放逐  作为给自己的惩罚  但这是为了什麽
I chose exile for my punishment, but what was it for?
我肯定是犯了特别可怕的错误
I must have done something terribly wrong...
而我不知道它究竟是什麽
And I've no evidence of what it was.
只能感受到痛苦  愧疚
Only pain, guilt...
无用  一无是处
Useless, worthless feelings!
我真希望我从没接手过梅崎的案子
I wish to God I'd never even taken Umezaki's case!
- 凯尔默的  - 什麽
- Kelmot's. - What?
是凯尔默的案子  你刚刚说了梅崎
Kelmot's case. You said Umezaki.
罗杰  茶泡好了
Roger. Tea's ready.
最好把这里收收
Best clear this up.
福尔摩斯先生  你现在想喝茶吗
Mr. Holmes. Would you like your tea now?
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes?
如果你死了  蜜蜂怎麽办
If you die... what'll happen to the bees?
我不知道
I haven't a clue.
一个人不可能解决所有问题
One can't solve everything.
据说这是用来召唤往生者的
Said to be used  to call for the dead.
死亡  哀悼  悲伤
Death, mourning, grief...
它们都平淡无奇
They're all commonplace.
而逻辑则很罕见
Logic is rare.
死者并不远
The dead are not so very far away.
他们只是在牆的另一面
They're just on the other side of the wall.
你究竟什麽时候说的这些
Now, whenever did you say that?
把你的小把戏用在别处吧  福尔摩斯先生
Ply your parlour tricks elsewhere, Mr. Holmes.
只要我还为我的丈夫洗衣服
My husband could never succeed at deception
他就不可能骗得过我
so long as I do his laundry.
我不太知道你是做什麽的
I don't know much about your profession,
但我猜测你常常受雇去跟踪女人
but I doubt predicting the future of women you're engaged to follow
预测她们的未来
is common practice.
这只是为了达到期待结果的一种手段
It was intended only as a means to achieve a desired result.
- 这是为了什麽  - 为了拖延你的行动
- That being what? - To delay your actions.
为了不让你去那个急于达成的会面
To keep you from this appointment you seem so eager to make.
在我今天瞥见你之前
Even before I glimpsed you today,
我就察觉到你对你丈夫的强烈情感
I'd gleaned some of the passionate feelings you have for your husband.
他夺走了你深爱的音乐
The man who took away the music you loved,
否定你从课堂中收穫的快乐
denied you the pleasures of your lessons,
甚至拒绝为孩子刻墓碑
even refused even to mark a child's grave.
所有这些都体现了你深深的厌恶
All these predicted your antipathy.
接下来我就看到了你的举动
And then I witnessed your actions.
假冒他签名
Forging his signature,
提取他的账户
drawing down his account,
购买毒药  咨询他的遗嘱
purchasing poison,  consulting his will,
计划和一个神秘男子逃跑 而他得到了不菲的报酬
planning an escape  with a mystery man who was paid a handsome fee.
在我看来
And all for my benefit.
这一系列有说服力的情况
A convincing set of circumstances,
表明了你谋杀你丈夫的动机
signalling your intention to murder your husband.
但有两处破绽
But for two errors.
首先要怪你的丈夫
We must place blame on your husband for the first.
如果凯尔默先生没有闯入西莫尔女士的工作室
If Mr. Kelmot had not blundered into Madame Schirmer's atelier...
把我从原计划中引开
and so taken me from my course,
你就不会在街上閒逛那麽久
you wouldn't have had  to loiter on the street
以致于十分可疑
for such a suspiciously long  period of time.
但你没有其他选择  只能閒逛
But you had no choice,   so loiter you did.
我也留意到你身上并没有任何迹象
I would also make the observation that there is nothing about you
表明你是那种逛橱窗只看不买的女人
that signifies the type of woman who enjoys window shopping,
特别当你所看的是一个动物标本剥制店的橱窗
especially the window of a taxidermist.
这就是第二个错吗
Was that the second error?
不  这只是第一个错误的证实
No, merely confirmation of the first.
第二个是无法避免的  也是更确凿的
The second was unavoidable, and all the more damning.
车站的那个男人
The man at the station.
他身上的一切 他的衣服  裤子上的补丁
Everything about him, his clothes,  the patches on his trousers,
他的双手  满是酸留下的疤痕和灼伤
his hands,  scarred and burned with acid,
表明了他的职业
announced his profession.
石匠
Stonemason.
金钱肯定是他最急迫需要的
Money must have been a dire necessity,
否则你绝对不会模仿你丈夫的签字
else you would never have forged your husband's signature.
这笔钱是为了买墓碑
The money was to pay for the headstones
这是你丈夫决不允许的
your husband would not allow.
为了格蕾丝和詹姆斯
For Grace. For James.
以及你自己
For you.
这样安排事情
Was arranging things to
让凯尔默先生看起来像是被蓄意谋杀的
make it look as if Mr. Kelmot was the intended victim
只是为了躲避我的追踪吗
simply to keep me off the trail?
当我看到那张卡片时  我太生气了
When I found the card... I was furious.
因为托马斯竟是那麽不瞭解我
That Thomas should know me so little
以致于需要雇一个侦探来调查真相
that he had need to employ a detective to uncover the truth.
然后我就想到了
Then it struck me,
如果有人能够瞭解  那个人肯定是你
if anyone could understand, it would be you.
托马斯觉得我疯了  因为我和我的孩子们讲话
Thomas thinks I'm mad because I speak to my children.
他不理解
He doesn't understand.
往生者们其实并不远
The dead are not so very far away.
他们只是
They're just...
在牆的另一边
on the other side of the wall.
而我们  就在这边  我们所有人都太
It's us, on this side, who are, all of us so...
孤独
Alone?
我一直都很孤独
I have been alone...
这辈子都是
all my life.
但我的思维能力是一种补偿
But with the compensations of the intellect.
- 这就足够了吗  - 可以说是
- And is that enough? - It can be.
只要他足够幸运能在这世上找到一个地方
If one is so fortunate as to find a place in the world.
在这里  他的孤独能够和另一个灵魂共处
And another soul with whom one's loneliness can reside.
你知道这样的地方吗  两个灵魂可以住在一起
Do you know a place where two such souls might reside?
这是个我从未接到过的邀请
It was an offer  unlike any I had ever received.
她想和我分享她的孤独
She wanted to share  her solitude with me.
之后我才意识到我的决定多麽可怕
It was only later I realised how fateful  my decision would be.
你有一个爱你的丈夫
You have a husband who loves you.
回家找他吧
Go home to him.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes...
我感激你
You have my thanks.
女士  我还可以为你做点什麽吗
What more, madam, could I do?
她将瓶子里的东西倒了出来
She had poured out   the contents of the bottle
并非蓄意地
and,  with no malice aforethought,
给那个无辜的目击者下了毒
poisoned the innocent witness.
如果这是约翰故事中的一个
If it had been  one of John's stories,
他会将它称为一个预示
he would have called it  a foreshadowing.
我和她共处的时间极为短暂
Our time together was fleeting.
事实上还不满一小时
Less than an hour, really.
但她的死却让我明白人性
Yet her death made me see that human nature was a mystery
是一个不能仅用逻辑去解释的谜
that logic alone could not illuminate.
我曾成功推理出她案件的来龙去脉
I had successfully deduced the facts of her case,
但我没有领会其中的深意
but I had failed to grasp their meaning.
我从没有如此感受到
Never had I felt
心中这样一种无法琢磨的空虚
such an incomprehensible emptiness within myself.
那之后我开始明白
Only then did I begin to understand
自己在这世上是多麽孤独
how utterly alone I was in the world.
哈德森太太写信给华生
Mrs. Hudson wrote to Watson.
他立刻就来了
He came at once.
我们一起在曾经的屋子里  度过了一个多月的时光
He stayed with me, in our old rooms, for a month more.
我将那个案子的所有细节都告诉了他
I told him about the case, everything in great detail.
他将我从绝望的边缘拉了回来
He brought me back from the brink.
之后  华生把这个故事写了下来
And then Watson wrote the story.
他将我描绘成一个英雄
He made me the hero.
那是他对我表示善意的方式
It was his way of bestowing a kindness.
除此之外他不知道还有什麽方法
He knew no other manner
能让他描述出此刻笔下的人物
in which to write the character he had created.
经过了这麽多年  约翰依旧不瞭解我
After all those years, John didn't know me at all.
为什麽他会把手套收起来  我只能靠猜了
Why he took the glove I can only surmise,
是不是担心它会勾起我的回忆
was it to prevent it becoming  too powerful a reminder,
担心它成为一口悲伤之井
to keep it from being  a well of sadness
引我重陷悲伤
to which I might return?
但他也没办法毁了它
But he could not bring himself to destroy it either.
在那之后  约翰和我渐渐疏远了
After that,  John and I were estranged.
三年后  他也离开了人世
Three years later,  he too was gone,
我们都不曾互相道别
without us ever having said goodbye.
这也是故事的真实结局
And thus concludes  the true story
女人不终天年
of a woman  who died before her time,
而男人  直到最近
and a man who, until recently,
才寿终正寝
was certain  he had outlived his.
罗杰又去看蜜蜂了
Roger with the bees?
很可能是的
Like as not.
我有些重要的事情要交代他
Must tell him something important.
你继续忙你的吧
You continue with whatever it was you were doing.
你问问他把洒水壶放哪儿去了
You might ask him where the watering can's got to!
救护车吗  对  这里是海德里庄园
Ambulance? Yes, this is Headly House.
- 海德里  - 对  麻烦快点
- Headly?   - Yes, quickly!
请带点肾上腺素液过来
And bring some supplies of adrenaline.
- 海德里庄园  - 对  海德里
-  Headly House?   - That's right, Headly!
罗杰
Roger?
Roger!
罗杰
Roger?
噢  罗杰  噢  不 不不不不不不
Oh, Roger. Oh, no! No, no, no, no, no, no!
罗杰  噢  罗杰
Roger. Oh, Roger!
福尔摩斯先生吗
Mr. Holmes?
我是吉尔伯特探长
It's Inspector Gilbert.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes?
我在这  探长
Yes, Inspector?
他们正在给那个男孩注射肾上腺素
They're giving the boy injections of adrenaline,
就像您说的那样  但是
as you said to, but...
他并不见转好
he's not looking good.
他当时正在躲那些蜜蜂
He was fleeing his attackers.
从他的脚印来看
His footprints.
看得出他当时非常惊慌失措
Their pattern shows that his flight was disorientated.
蜂群肯定一直追著他叮咬
The must have followed him in their attack.
而在他失去意识之前
And before he lost consciousness,
他的皮肤一定出现过潮红
his skin would have flushed,
同时伴随著灼痛感
accompanied by burning pain...
血压迅速下降  导致虚弱
A drop in blood pressure, weakness.
他的喉咙和嘴巴也会红肿
His throat and mouth would be swollen
这也是为什麽他无法呼救
which explains why he didn't call for help.
然后心率下降
Then a drop in heart rate...
呼吸困难
Inability to breathe...
陷入休克
Shock.
您知道他对蜜蜂过敏吗
Did you know he was allergic to bees?
我确定他不会
I was certain he wasn't.
不  不  门罗夫人
No, no! No, Mrs. Munro, no!
你不能那样做
You mustn't do that!
我的儿子  醒不过来了
My son... won't wake.
他可能永远也不会醒来了
He may never wake.
他们在早上之前一直把我支开
They sent me away till morning.
你甚至都没有打算
You didn't even have the decency
告诉我他究竟怎麽了
to tell me what'd happened to him!
我不觉得这能有什麽帮助
I didn't think it would make a difference.
我是他的母亲
I'm his mother!
I'm his mother...
你把他从我身边偷走了
And you stole him from me!
他是我的全部
He's all I had!
现在我失去他了
And I've lost him now.
为什麽承受这一切的不是你
Why wasn't it you they did it to?
- 这都该由你承受  - 这不是那些蜜蜂的错
It should've been you!  - The bees were not to blame.
你只在乎那些蜜蜂
They're all you care about!
不  我在乎的是罗杰
No! I care about Roger.
我非常在乎他
I care about him very much.
我养的那些蜜蜂  并没有蛰他
The bees... didn't do it.
不是那些蜜蜂的错
The bees were not to blame.
蛰他的是黄蜂
It was the wasps!
罗杰试著弄清楚谁杀死了那些蜜蜂
Roger was trying to find out what was killing the bees.
于是他就到处找  他找到了黄蜂的巢
And he did. He found the wasps' nest.
他想要阻止它们捕杀蜜蜂
He had to stop them wiping out the bees.
所以他可能做了最糟糕的事情
And so he did the worst possible thing.
他想用洒水壶浇那些黄蜂
He tried to drown them with water from his can.
你怎麽知道是黄蜂蛰的
How do you know it was them?
蜜蜂蛰人的时候会射出刺  而黄蜂不会
Bees leave their stings. Wasps don't.
罗杰的脸上没有刺
There were no stings left in Roger's face.
当他们发起攻击的时候  他用洒水壶朝它们洒水
And when they attacked, he dropped the watering can
然后跑去保护那些蜜蜂
and ran up to protect the bees.
他的脚印显示他从蜂房到了黄蜂巢  然后又回到了蜂房
There are his footprints from the apiary to the nest and back.
- 他想救那些蜜蜂  - 是的
- He was trying to save the bees.  - Yes.
是的
Yes.
从前  有一个女人
There was a woman, once.
我认识她不到一天
I knew her less than a day.
只聊过一刻钟的天
A quarter of an hour's conversation.
她需要我的帮助
She needed my help.
她是如此渴望被人理解
She needed so desperately to be understood by someone...
被我理解
Me.
所以我仔细研究了她那个案件的细节
So, I laid out the particulars of her case as I saw them...
我想是为了取悦她
To her satisfaction, I thought.
我看著她离开
I watched her walk away.
几个小时之后  她结束了自己的生命
And within hours she'd ended her life.
为了搞清楚她为何如此绝望
By identifying the cause of her despair with such clarity,
我曾经给了她一份她想要的全权委託书
I'd given her carte blanche to do just as she intended.
我当时应该倾我所能救她的命的
I should've done whatever it took to save her.
当时我应该骗她  编造一个故事
Lie to her, make up a story.
当她哭泣的时候陪在她身边
Take her by the hand and hold her as she wept,
跟她说  来跟我一起住吧
and said, "Come live with me.
让我们两个人一起孤独吧
Let us be alone together."
但我当时很害怕
But I was fearful.
也很自私
Selfish.
她是我
She's the reason...
到这里来养蜜蜂的原因
I came here to my bees,
正因那样  我不能再伤害任何一个人
so that I couldn't harm anyone ever again.
我会搬出去住
I'm leaving you the house.
离开你  还有罗杰
You and Roger.
房子  土地  蜂房  这里的一切一切
House, grounds, apiary, everything within and without.
我心意已决
And as I shan't change my mind
我相信你会理解  这样的话
on this point, you will see, I trust,
一切都会简单许多
that it will be greatly less complicated for all concerned
只要你们俩不要去
if the two of you don't go off to...
某些地方  比如  朴茨茅斯
... somewhere like... Portsmouth.
门夫人
Mrs. Munro?
罗杰醒了
Roger's awake.
尊敬的梅崎先生
Dear Mr.Umezaki,
去信告知  我终于
I write to tell you that I have at last
回想起与你父亲的会面
recalled my meeting  with your father.
有个女人  因为没能帮她侦破案件而死
A woman had died because I failed to solve her case.
我的心中满是罪恶感与愧疚
Guilt and recrimination  having taken their toll on me,
因为我远远没有人们想像的那麽厉害
my powers  were far from at their best
当我收到一封加急信
when I received  an urgent message
通知我去第欧根尼俱乐部
summoning me to the Diogenes Club
见我的哥哥麦考夫
to meet  with my brother Mycroft.
这位先生想要提供服务
This gentleman has made an offer of service.
他希望能为国王效力
He wishes to work for the Crown.
我来这里接受考验  福尔摩斯先生
I'm here to be tested, Mr. Holmes.
我非常希望能有所贡献
I very much want to be of use.
您觉得我合适吗
Do you think that I am suited?
当然了  先生
I'm sure, sir.
很好  还有一件小事情要说
Good. There is one minor issue.
梅崎先生已在日本成家  还有了一个孩子
Mr. Umezaki has a wife and child in Japan.
他想知道让孩子修什麽课程好
He wonders what would be the best course.
写一封信告诉他  你打算继续留在伦敦
Write a letter saying you plan to stay on in England.
可能要很久才能回去
Could be a long while until your return.
你的父亲接著为英国国王效力了很久
Your father went on to serve the British Empire  for many years
一直忠心耿耿  并且声名远扬
in absolute secrecy and with the greatest distinction,
从
from...
马来海峡
the Malay... Straits...
一直到阿拉伯海
to the Arabian Sea.
他勇敢  真诚  高雅
He was a man of courage, heart and dignity,
同时他拥有挚爱的妻子和儿子
of whom a beloved wife  and cherished son
这真是值得骄傲的事情
may be deservedly proud.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
吾友  约翰
My friend John.
我的哥哥麦考夫
My brother Mycroft.
哈德森夫人
Mrs. Hudson.
益男梅崎
Masuo Umezaki.
麻野梅崎
Maya... Umezaki.
安
Ann.
那代表谁
And who is that one for?
我  你
Me. You.
暂时还不会死  对吧
Well, not yet awhile, surely?
你把该做的事情都做了吗
Did you finish what you had to do?
是的  都做了
Yes, I did.
我完成了小说的处女作
My first foray into the world of fiction.
人不能带著遗憾离开这个世界
One shouldn't leave this life without a sense of completion.
你可以把这个写在你的小说里
You can use this in one of your stories.
玻璃  蜜蜂
A glass, a bee...
还有你
and Roger.
告诉我怎麽料理那些蜜蜂
Show me how to knock them out.
去吧
Go on.
- 蜂后掌管著整个蜂群  - 嗯
- The queen runs the colony.  - Mm-hmm.
雄蜂为蜂后效力
The drones service the queen.
工蜂则勤勤恳恳地工作
The workers do the work.
难道不是吗
Isn't it true?